ALEJANDRO MATA ÁLVAREZ

Financial Data Scientist

Madrid, ES in/alemalvarez +1 (279) 237-8328 alemalvarez@icloud.com

Objectives

Bringing together academic studies in both technology and finance from Spain and practical experience in California's financial sector, my goal as a financial data scientist is to eventually lead AI model development. With a solid foundation in Python programming and machine learning, alongside insights gained from working in financial markets, my focus is on uncovering valuable insights from complex data. I aim to introduce practical solutions that enhance decision-making at the intersection of technology and finance.

Work Experience

Financial Data Scientist

January 2024 to present.

Student Investment Fund at Sacramento State

Sacramento, California

As a financial data scientist, I led Python script development using Bloomberg Terminal data for security analysis, financial visualization, and trading strategy formulation for a million-dollar investment fund. I also explored machine learning solutions for trend identification and security analysis. Finally, I designed and implemented expected return estimates crucial for portfolio management.

IoT Trainee Vibia Lighting

April 2023 to August 2023

Barcelona, Spain

In my position at Vibia Lighting, I was responsible for designing and building a data driven IoT testing workflow within the Jira ecosystem. This involved utilizing Python-GraphQL to retrieve and analyze test results, as well as designing Power BI dashboards to visualize insights derived from the data. I collaborated closely with different stakeholders and managed to successfully communicate with them to ensure the successful implementation of these solutions.

Education

Business Administration - Data Science

2023-2024

California State University

Sacramento, California

GPA: 4.0/4.0 - Dean's Honor List

Joined an exchange program under a scholarship, focusing on statistics and data analytics. As part of the Data Science Club, I worked on their team projects and got an honorable mention in the 2023 Business Analytics Competition for my machine learning model on loan default prediction.

Machine Learning Specialization Stanford University Online

2023

Online

Grade: 100%

Completed the specialization by building over 15 distinct ML models up from the mathematical fundamentals. Some of the topics were linear and logistic regression, tree-based models (Random Forest, XGBoost...), deep learning, clustering, recommender systems and reinforcement learning.

Business Administration - Finance

2022-2023

Universitat de Barcelona

Barcelona, Spain

Grade: 8.1/10.0

While in Barcelona, I focused on finance, applied logical problem solving, and decision sciences, excelling in a mathematical decision-making course with a grade of honor.

Telecommunication Systems Engineering

2019-2022

Universidad de Valladolid

Valladolid, Spain

Grade: 7.8/10.0

Excelled on mathematics, covering advanced calculus, linear algebra, linear systems, signal analysis, and statistics. Simultaneously, I developed proficiency in software development, mainly in C-based languages, along with essential tools like Git and software deployment techniques. For my bachelor's thesis, I built a deep learning tool for diagnosing Alzheimer's disease.

Volunteering

Volunteer Radio Co-Host

January 2024 to present.

KSSU at Associated Students Inc.

Sacramento, California

Created, scripted, and hosted the successful weekly radio program 'Beat 'N Tracks', researching and explaining world music to 5,000+ listeners.

Skills

- Financial Data Science
- Python
- TensorFlow

- Machine Learning
- Creative Problem-
 - **Investment Strategies**
- Reinforcement Learning Algorithmic Trading

- Mathematical Thinking

Financial Instruments

Solving

Predictive Modelling